Register of the Kenneth Hugh De Courcy papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Kenneth Hugh De Courcy papers
1934-1991
79080
De Courcy, Kenneth Hugh, 1909-
8 microfilm reels, 1 folder (1.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Microfilm of correspondence, memoranda, depositions and other legal documents, minutes, and writings, relating to world politics, British foreign policy, espionage in Great Britain, the Imperial Policy Group, political views of the Duke of Windsor, and business affairs of and legal proceedings against British financier and publisher K. H. De Courcy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Originals in possession of: K. H. De Courcy.
Biographical Note
1909 November 6 Born, Oldham, Lancashire, Great Britain
(?) Educated, Kings College School, London
1933 Honary Secretary, unoffical committee on Conservative Party policy, chairman Sir Reginald Banks
1934-1942 (?) Honorary Secretary, Imperial Policy Group
1938-1976 Editor, proprietor of Intelligence Digest
(?) Chairman Ridgeway Courcy and Company
1950 Married Rosemary Catherine Baker
1951-1976 Editor, proprietor of Weekly Review
1953-1964 Member of the committee of the Exangelical Alliance which organized "crusades" by Billy Graham in Great Britain
196? Chairman, Overseas Land Purchasing Trust
1963-1964 Trial and convication for forgery and other offences
1968 Released from prison
1969-1972 Editor, Banker's Digest
1973 Marriage dissolved
1973- Editor, Special Office Brief
1977 Chancellor, Order of the Three Orders
Scope and Content of Collection
Microfilm of correspondence, memoranda, depositions and other legal documents, minutes, and writings, relating to world politics, British foreign policy, espionage in Great Britain, the Imperial Policy Group, political views of the Duke of Windsor, and business affairs of and legal proceedings against British financier and publisher K. H. De Courcy.
Arrangement
Arranged into six series: Imperial Policy Group, 1934-1942, Correspondence, 1936-1983, Correspondence with F. Roy Cattell, 1953-1957, Subject File, circa 1936-1984, Trial and appeals, 1946-1984, and Speeches and Writings, 1983-1984.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Imperial Policy Group (London); Espionage, Russian--Great Britain.; World politics.; Great Britain--Foreign relations.; Edward VIII, King of Great Britain, 1894-1972.
Container List
- Imperial Policy Group, 1934-1942
  Minutes of National Citizens' Union, and later Imperial Policy Group, committees and sub-committees with related reports and correspondence and other papers.
  - Minutes of the National Citizens Union Policy Committee (which was reconstituted in October 1934 as the Imperial Policy Group) and of the Imperial Policy Group Executive Committee and sub-committees on: Empire; foreign policy; House of Lords reform; organization of propaganda; shipping; taxation; and unemployment, 1934-1942 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Report of Foreign Affairs Mission on Central Europe with a covering letter to Sir Robert Vansittart, 1936 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 3)
    (photocopy)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other papers found in 1 above, 1937-1983 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1936-1983
  Correspondence of Kenneth De Courcy, arranged alphabetically by correspondent
  - Belchem, General David, 1978-1981 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 5)
    Subjects include: British military strategy and preparedness; USSR strategy
  - Butler, R. A., 1956-1961 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 6)
    Subjects include: British domestic politics; Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland; Field Marshall Bernard Montgomery; Near East; Rhodesia (Zimbabwe); Trade Union leaders' private talks with Conservative Party leaders; USSR foreign policy
  - Douglas-Home, sir Alec (Lord Home), 1975-(1983?) (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
    Subjects include: East-West relations; Near East; Rhodesia (Zimbabwe)
  - Eden, Sir Anthony, 1951-1952 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
    Subjects include: possibility of recruiting opposition leaders to the Conservative Government (Clement Davies and Walter Citrine are named); Persia (Iran)
  - Fisher, Nigel, 1974-1983 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 9)
    Subjects include: Afghanistan; British defense policy; British domestic politics; Near East; Poland; Rhodesia (Zimbabwe); South Africa; USSR. Also contains correspondence from Colonel R. Butler, "Chief of Staff" to General Walter Walker. (See also box 2 folder 6)
  - Foreign Office, Great Britain, 1951 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 10)
    Concerns Roy De Groot, former circulation agent for Intelligence Digest in the USA
  - Hankey, Lord Maurice, 1955-1962 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 11)
    Subjects include: Conservative Party leadership; Eastern Mediterranean; Near East
  - Hogg, Quintin, (Lord Hailsham), 1956-1962 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 12)
    Subjects include: Central African Federation; Conservative Party leadership; John F. Kennedy, President of the USA; Near East; Trade Union leaders' private talks with the Conservative Party leaders; USSR foreign policy
  - Inskip, Sir Thomas (Lord Caldecote), 1936-1943 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Subjects include: Czechoslovakia crisis, 1938; France, preparedness for war in late 1930s; Great Britain preparedness for war in late 1930s; Imperial Policy Group overseas propaganda; Kenneth De Courcy's complaints about M.I.5 interference with his mail and telephone; Kenneth De Courcy's attempts to become a conservative party candidate; Kenneth De Courcy's attempts to obtain exemption from "directed employment" under war-time regulations, World War, 1939-1945, possibility of a negotiated peace; World War, 1939-1945, Norway campaign
  - Lennox-Boyd, Alan, 1956-1958 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 1)
    Subjects include: Central African Federation; conservative Party leadership; Suez crisis
  - Londonderry, Lord and Lady, 1940-1941 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 2)
    Concerning war-time foreign policy and strategy, particularly in respect of air-power
  - Londonderry, Lord and Lady, 1946-1953 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 3)
    Subjects include: Conservative Party organization and finance; evangelism as an anti-dote to socialism
  - Salisbury, Lord, 1951-1952 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 4)
    Concerns infiltration of the Civil Service in Great Britain by Soviet sympathizers
  - Vansittart, Lord Robert, 1951-1953 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Walker, General Walter, and Burnand, P., 1973-1976 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 6)
    Subjects include: Civil Assistance, an organization founded by General Walter to oppose subversion; attempts by the Ministry of Defense to restrict General Walter in the expression of his views on defense policy
  - War Office, Great Britain, 1946 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 7)
    Concerns Kenneth De Courcy's complaints regarding obstruction of his activities as a publicist
  - War Office, Great Britain, 1951 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 8)
    Concerns Kenneth De Courcy's complaints regarding harassment of Intelligence Digest by M.I.5
  - Windsor, Duke of (King Edward VIII) and Duchess of (Mrs. Simpson), 1946-1987 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 9)
    Subjects include: abdication crisis; British domestic politics; British foreign policy; relations between the Duke of Windsor and his brother King George VI
- Correspondence of F. Roy Cattell, 1953-1957
  Correspondence of Rev. F. Roy Cattell, Secretary of the Evangelical Alliance
  - Correspondence of F. Roy Cattell as Secretary of the Evangelical Alliance, 1953-1957. (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    Subjects include: Billy Graham's 1954 and 1955 British "Crusades"; politically accented reporting of the "Crusades" in Kenneth De Courcy's publications; suspected Communist sympathies of a member of the Evangelical Alliance committee
- Subject File, (1936?)-1984
  Notes, Correspondence, memoranda, reports and memoirs, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Abuse of administrative power by civil and military authorities of Great Britain, complained of by Kenneth De Courcy's, 1946-1984 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 12)
    Correspondents include Lord Vansittart and Sir Anthony Eden
  - Current Affairs, 1974 (Reel 2, Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Current Affairs, 1983 (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Current Affairs, 1984 (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 15)
  - De Courcy, Michael, 1950-1984 (Reel 3, Box 2, Folder 16)
    Correspondence and other papers re Michael De Courcy and alleged attempts by M.I.5 to penetrate Intelligence Digest through him
  - France, foreign relations and military preparedness in 1938, (1983?) (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Prison memoirs of Kenneth De Courcy relating to Wormwood Scrubs Prison, London, Great Britain, (1968?) (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 2)
    Contains reference to the escape of George Blake
  - Subversive activities of Soviet sympathizers in the Civil Service of Great Britain, 1947-1983 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Windsor, Duke of (King Edward VIII) (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 4)
    aides-memoirs written by Kenneth De Courcy, dated 1936-1949 and apparently re-copied later
  - Windsor, Duke of (King Edward VIII), copies of correspondence and various notes, 1946-1949; 1979-(1983?) (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Windsor, Duke of (King Edward VIII), correspondence and other papers, 1978-1982 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 6)
    Concerns allegations that the Duke considered committing treason by becoming a party to peace negotiations with Nazi Germany
  - World Politics, 1938-1940 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 7)
    Concerns many aspects of European and Near Eastern affairs including: Czechoslovakia crisis, 1938; Russo-German relations; World War, 1939-1945, Norway campaign; World War, 1939-1945, possibility of a negotiated pace. Correspondents include: General Brecard (France); H. A. Butler; Sir Eric Geddes; M. Leger (France); H. Lemery (France)
  - World Politics, 1938-1940 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 8)
    Consists almost entirely of copies of items in Folder 7 above, also contains a detailed report on the equipment and strength of the USSR Air Force, 1939
  - World Politics, 1939 (Reel 3, Box 3, Folder 9)
    Intelligence reports concerning the foreign policy and military capacity of Estonia, Finland, Latvia, Lithuania, Norway, Poland and Sweden, prepared by Alastair Campbell on the basis of interviews, written materials, and travel in the countries named
  - World War, 1939-1945 (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 10)
    diplomatic history, possibility of a negotiated peace, 1939-1940
- Trial and Appeals, 1946-1984
  Correspondence, memoranda, affidavits, company stock applications, contracts, powers of attorney, trust deeds, and related papers concerning Kenneth De Courcy's 1963-1964 trial and conviction and subsequent attempts to appeal against the conviction and to obtain publicity in respect of the case, also concerning property transitions in Canada and Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), arranged chronologically
  - 1946-1963 (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 11)
    Subversive activities of Soviet sympathizers in Great Britain, Kenneth De Courcy's opposition to subversion, and the circumstance of Kenneth De Courcy's trial
  - 1956-(1983?) (Reel 4, Box 3, Folder 12-13)
    Trial counts 8 and 9: forgery in the form of issuing ante-dated documents. Other subjects include: Nassau anti-Communist conference organized by Kenneth De Courcy, 1962; proposed Art Digest and Bankers' Digest magazines; Rhodesia (Zimbabwe) property dealings
  - 1957-1972 (Reel 4, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Trial count 4: falsification of Overseas Land Purchasing Trust records. Other subjects include: Rhodesia (Zimbabwe), politics and business, Salisbury, Rhodesia (Harare, Zimbabwe), housing construction
  - 1957-(1983?) (Reel 4, Box 4, Folder 3)
    Trial counts 4 and 13: forgery. Other subject include Salisbury, Rhodesia (Harare, Zimbabwe) housing construction (1 of 2)
  - 1957-(1983?) (Reel 5, Box 4, Folder 4)
    Trial counts 4 and 13: forgery. Other subject include Salisbury, Rhodesia (Harare, Zimbabwe) housing construction (2 of 2)
  - 1958-1966 (Reel 5, Box 4, Folder 5-6)
    Stock application in respect of Sarsden Consolidated Properties Ltd. Of Toronto, Canada with related papers
  - 1958-(1983?) (Reel 5, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    Kenneth De Courcy's campaign to prove the complicity of the Police in a conspiracy to obtain a conviction against him, particularly by means of concealing documentary evidence. Other subjects include Sarsden Consolidated Properties of Toronto, Canada
  - 1959-1972 (Reel 5, Box 5, Folder 3)
    Trial count 3: (improper relations between Overseas Land Purchasing Trust and Sarsden Properties Ltd.?)
  - 1960 (Reel 5, Box 5, Folder 4)
    Fraud involving Dollar Land Holdings Ltd.
  - 1960-1971 (Reel 5, Box 5, Folder 5)
    Trial Count 9: forgery in the form of issuing ante-dating documents, concerns complex relations between Dollar Land Holdings ltd.; Overseas Land Purchasing Trust, Reserved Property Trust, Peter Von Dumreicher and Kenneth De Courcy
  - 1960-1972 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 6)
    Trial counts 13, 14, and 16: perjury and contempt of court, concerns control of New Townships Ltd.
  - 1960-1984 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 7)
    Forgery in the form of issuing ante-dated documents in respect of the Reserved Property Trust
  - 1964-1981 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 8)
    Kenneth De Courcy's attempts to appeal against conviction and to obtain publicity in respect of his case
  - 1978-1983 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 9)
    Evidence submitted to the Royal Commission on Criminal Procedure by Kenneth De Courcy
  - 1983 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 10)
    Questions submitted to Kenneth De Courcy by the Archivist of the Hoover Instituion on War, Revolution, and Peace with the former's replies
  - 1984 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1984 (Reel 6, Box 5, Folder 12)
    Memorandum by Kenneth De Courcy
- Speeches and Writings, 1983-1984
  Printed copies of a news-sheet and a booklet by Kenneth De Courcy
  - Special Office Brief, nos. 237-247, 1983-1984 (Reel 7, Box 5, Folder 13)
  - A Watcher on the Threshold (Kenneth De Courcy?) The Carolingian Crown of France Kilbrittain Newspapers Ltd., Dublin, Ireland, 1984 (Reel 7, Box 5, Folder 14)
- Increment, October 1984 (Reel 7, Box 5, Folder 15)
  Two letters to De Courcy
- Increment, May 1985, 1980-1984
  - Typewritten transcript of an interview of K. H. De Courcy conducted by Charles Palm, 1983 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Letters from John Straker to Sir Carl Aarvold, David Parsons, Nicholas Ridley, Margaret Thatcher, Sir Michael Havers, 1980-1984 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 2)
    relating to the trial of K. H. De Courcy
- Increment, July 1986, 1985-1986 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 3)
  Correspondence between John Straker and the Lord Chancellor's Department, 1985-1986, relating to the trail; the Lord Chancellor's speech of welcome to the American Bar Association in Westminster on July 15, 1985; and a clipping relating to Lord Halisham, 1985
- Increment, September 1986, 1981 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 4)
  Carbon copy of John Straker's letter to the Private Secretary to the Lord Chancellor, dated 19 July 1986; and the 31 May 1986 issue of News of the World containing an article on the Jeremy Thorpe scandal
- Increment, December 1987 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 5)
  Correspondence, 1987, relating to the Duke of Windsor and to various aspects of British politics and society
- Increment, June, 1991 (Reel 7, Box 6, Folder 6)
  Correspondence and writings, 1991, relating to Kenneth De Courcy's trial in 1963-1964